Inventory of David D. Laitin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
David D. Laitin papers
1951-2007
2015C6
Hoover Institution Archives
23 manuscript boxes (9.6 linear feet)
The David D. Laitin papers contain speeches, notes, writings, correspondence, dissertations, pamphlets, bulletins, serial issues, and other printed matter relating to the history, language, political, and social conditions of Somalia in particular and the Horn of Africa in general.
Laitin, David D.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
David D. Laitin was born on June 4, 1945 in Brooklyn, New York. He received his B.A. in political science with high honors from Swarthmore College in 1967, his M.A. in political science from the University of California, Berkeley in 1968, and his Ph.D. in political science from the University of California, Berkeley in 1974.
Laitin is the James T. Watkins IV and Elise V. Watkins Professor of Political Science at Stanford University. Professor Laitin has also taught at the University of California, Berkeley, University of Chicago, and the University of California, San Diego. He has written many articles, books, and conference papers. His specialty is comparative politics, and he has completed fieldwork in, and is an expert on, the countries of Somalia, Nigeria, Catalonia, Estonia, and France.
Scope and Contents note
The David D. Laitin papers include materials collected over decades, from the time Laitin was a Peace Corps volunteer in the 1960s through the 2000s. The materials primarily relate to the history, politics, language, education, and economy of Somalia, with a few documents on Nigeria. Most are in the form of correspondence, speeches and writings, pamphlets of various political groups within the Somali political landscape, bulletins, dissertations, and serial issues. Additional material includes Horn of Africa related topics, such as Ethiopia and Eritrea, and other printed matter. A large portion of the collection was used as research material for Laitin's books and articles, including Politics, Language and Thought: The Somali Experience (University of Chicago Press, 1977), and Somalia: Nation in Search of a State, co-authored with Said Samatar (Westview, 1987).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Speeches and Writings, Office File, Correspondence, Subject File, and Printed Matter.
Related Materials
Donald S. Rothchild papers, Hoover Institution Archives
I. William Zartman collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Somali Subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Leslie Gottesman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Henze papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Boutros Boutros Ghali papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Ethiopian subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Eritrea subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Nigeria subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
George D. Jenkins papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Somalia--Economic conditions.; Somalia--History.; Somalia--Politics and government.; Somalia--Social conditions.
- Speeches and Writings, 1976-2007 (Box 1-4)
  - American Political Science Association, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "Changes in Ideas of the Somali Nation,", 1982 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - "Somalia: Civil War and International Intervention," Columbia-Ford Conference, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "The Compliant Foreign Policy of the Dependent State Revisited: Empirical Linkages and Lessons from the Case of Somalia,", 1987 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - General Somali data, notes, and tables, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "Hegemony and Religious Conflict,", 1982 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Hussein M. Adam papers, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Journal excerpt, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lecture notes, Emerson class, SUNY, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Lecture notes, Political Science Department, University of California, San Diego (UCSD), undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Mali and Somalia Under Civilian and Military Rule: The Prospects for Radical Socialism,", 1978 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Messages and notes, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Revolutionary Change in Somalia," Middle East Research and Information Project (MERIP), undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - "My Study Embedded in a Theory of the State," revisions of chapter 10 comments, 1983 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "The New Media in State and National Development: The Changing Context of Somali Poetry,", undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "Africa: Continuity and Change in the 1980s," Naval Postgraduate School, 1980 May 1-2 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "Somalia and the World Economy" for Review of African Political Economy (ROAPE), notes and correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Notes for Bellagio talks, State vs. Ethnic Claims paper, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Notes for Colliers, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Notes on Somalia, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "The Ogaadeen Question and Changes in Somali Identity,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "The OAU and the Ogaadeen Question: Towards a Solution,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - "The Political Economy of Military Rule in Somalia,", 1976 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "Politics, Language and Thought: The Somali Experience,", 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Preface and notes, undated (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - "Religion and Ancestral City Among the Yoruba: A Study in the Rise and Persistence of Ethnicity," draft, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - "Review of I. M. Lewis' A Modern History of Somalia: Nation and State in the Horn of Africa,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "The Revolutionary Development of the Somali Language," Adam, Hussein M., undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - "Somali Becomes the Official Language,", undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Somalia: America's Newest Ally,", 1984 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "Somalia: Civil War and International Intervention,", undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "Somalia: Civil War and International Intervention," revision for Columbia University Press, 1997 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "Somalia: Intervention in Internal Conflict,", 2001 December 7 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Somalia and the World Economy," draft, Laitin, David D. and Samatar, Said S., undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "Somalia's Domestic Coalitions and the Prospects for Conciliation with Ethiopia," abstract, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "Somalia's Economy Under Military Rule,", 1978 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Somalia's Military Government and Scientific Socialism,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "Somalia's Transitional Federal Government,", 2007 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "Some Trends in Somalia's Political Economy,", 1983 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Speeches and writings, notes and drafts, 1983, 2004, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Statements before the House Foreign Affairs Sub-Committee on Africa, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "Tensions on Africa's Horn: The Somali Claims in International Perspective,", 1976 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "Hearings on Appropriations to the Horn of Africa," testimony of Dr. David D. Laitin, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - "A Thick Description of Abner Cohen's Hausa Migrants,", undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - "U.S. Policy in the Horn,", 1983 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Office File, 1981-1992 (Box 4)
  - Business cards, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Grants, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Invitations, 1983, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Library of Congress, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Receipts, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Correspondence, 1973-2005 (Box 4-7)
  - Abdi, Said Yusuf, 1978-1979, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Abdi, Yonis M., 1974 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Abdillahi, Ibrahim Haji, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Abdullahi, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Abuje, F. L., 1973 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Abukar, Hassan M., 1982 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Abukgr, Hassan, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Adam, Xusen M., 1978-1979 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Addou, Abdullahi, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Ahmed, Abdalla, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Ali, Osman Sultan, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Amina, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Andrew, undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Andrzejewski, B. W., 1976-1978 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Ardon, 1975 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Armstrong, James C., 1980 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Arnie, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Aronoff, Mike, 1976-1982 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Arriola, Leonardo Rafael, undated (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - Atiyeh, Victor, 1975 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - Bapham, Lewis, Editor of Harper's, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - Baron, Williams, 1980 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Bartlett, Dewey F., 1978 (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Bender, Gerald J., Coleman, James C., and Sklar, Richard L., 1982 (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Bennoune, Mahfoud, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - Bienen, Henry, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - Birkendkamp, Dean, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - Blackburn, Bob, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 37)
  - Brass, Paul, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 38)
  - Brokensha, David, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 39)
  - Brookhart, John R., 1978 (Box-folder 4: 40)
  - Bowman, Larry W., 1981-1985 (Box-folder 4: 41)
  - Boyd, James M., 1976 (Box-folder 4: 42)
  - Büscher, Horst, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 43)
  - C. B. Peggy, undated (Box-folder 4: 44)
  - Cahill, Kevin M., 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4: 45)
  - Cali, Axmed F. "Idaajaa,", 1978, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 46)
  - Callaghy, Tom, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Cambridge University Press, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Campbell, Jeanne E., 1986 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Cassanelli, Lee V., 1978, 1983, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Charles, 1978, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Clough, Michael, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Coleman, James C., 1979, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - The Commission (Committee) of the Somali Language, undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Cottino, Elisabetta Forni, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Davidson, Basil, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Dean, Virginia Lee Barnes, 1984, undated (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Derie, Arden, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Deutsch, Karl W., 1978 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Dirie, Idris H., 1981 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Dixon, Julian C., 1983 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Dwyer, David and Yankee, Everyl, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Edan, Ali A., 1982 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Editors of The Atlantic Monthly, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Esa, Ahmed H., Dow, Michael, and McDonald, G. C., 1981 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Fellow Somalists, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Foltz, William J., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Fowzi, Mohamed Hassan, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Frederick, Melinda J., 1982 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - Furgeson, Sally, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Ganzglass, Martin R., 1983 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Garcia, Chris F., 1977 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Geertz, Clifford, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Gelyo, Nabad, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Geshecter, Charles, 1976-1982 (Box-folder 5: 29)
  - Gilbert, Miriam, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 30)
  - Golden, Peter B., 1983 (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - Graves, Becky, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 32)
  - Gugel, Gregory C., 1989 (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Gulaid, Ibrahim Haji Abdullahi, 1976 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Gure, Ahmed A., 1988 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Gumey, Charles B., 2005 (Box-folder 5: 36)
  - Hamrick, Sam, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 37)
  - Hansen, Katy, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 38)
  - Harbeson, John W., 1978-1979 (Box-folder 5: 39)
  - Hass, Ernest B., 1973 (Box-folder 5: 40)
  - Hawley, Edward A., 1976 (Box-folder 5: 41)
  - Heine, Bernd, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 42)
  - Hill, Bruce, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 43)
  - Hill, Frances, 1977 (Box-folder 5: 44)
  - Horowitz, Irving Lewis, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 45)
  - Hull, Thomas N., 1984 (Box-folder 5: 46)
  - Hussain, Asaf, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 47)
  - Hussein, Abdinasir Abdullahi, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 5: 48)
  - Hussein, Ahmed A., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 49)
  - Hussein, Saleh J., 1978 (Box-folder 5: 50)
  - Hyland, William G., 1974 (Box-folder 5: 51)
  - Ibrahim, Ibrahim Bulo, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 52)
  - Ilchman, Warren F., 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5: 53)
  - Instituto Poligrafico Dello Stato, 1976 (Box-folder 5: 54)
  - Intriligator, Michael D., 1983 (Box-folder 5: 55)
  - Jabir, Hussein, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 56)
  - Jackson, Stephan, 2004 (Box-folder 5: 57)
  - Janssen, Harry, 1976 (Box-folder 5: 58)
  - Jibril, Maxamed, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 59)
  - Jimale, Aden M., 1976 (Box-folder 5: 60)
  - Jimale, Ahmed M., 1973-1975, undated (Box-folder 5: 61)
  - Joann and Ambara, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 62)
  - Joel, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 63)
  - John, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 64)
  - Johnson, John William, 1978, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 65)
  - Jones, Victor, 1976 (Box-folder 5: 66)
  - Jules-Rosette, Bennetta, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 5: 67)
  - Junne, Gerd, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Kaher, Miles, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Kasper, Ben, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Keohane, Robert, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Kimble, David, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Kirpatrick, Evron M., 1976 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Kitchen, Helen, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Kraus, Jon, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Kulick, Gil, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Labahn, Thomas, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Labahn, Thomas and Adam, Hussein M., 1982-1983 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Landis, Marin, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Law, Cordham, 1974 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Leadbeater, Lea, 1986 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Leitenberg, Milton, 2001 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Lenny, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Lewis, I. M., 1976-1982 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Loughran, Katheryne and John L., 1978, undated (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Lustick, Ian, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Lyman, Princeton, 1974 (Box-folder 6: 20)
  - Lynes, Debbie, 1986 (Box-folder 6: 21)
  - Lynes, Deborah, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 22)
  - Macmillan Education Corporation, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 23)
  - Makinda, Samuel M., 1983 (Box-folder 6: 24)
  - Manuscript Editor of The New Yorker, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 25)
  - Markakis, John, 1980, 1984 (Box-folder 6: 26)
  - Martin, C. J., 1976 (Box-folder 6: 27)
  - Matthews, Bill, undated (Box-folder 6: 28)
  - Mbogo, Chris, 2005 (Box-folder 6: 29)
  - McKenzie, Sara Jane W., 1985 (Box-folder 6: 30)
  - Miller, Janet, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 31)
  - Miskell, John, 1977, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 32)
  - Mitchell, Chris R., 1975 (Box-folder 6: 33)
  - Mohamed, Abdirahman D., 1983 (Box-folder 6: 34)
  - Mohamed, Ali Ibrahim, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 35)
  - Mohamed, Ali N., 1980-1990 (Box-folder 6: 36)
  - Mohamed, H., 1982 (Box-folder 6: 37)
  - Mohammed, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 38)
  - Mohamud, Abdinur, 1986 (Box-folder 6: 39)
  - Mungai, K. B., 1977 (Box-folder 6: 40)
  - Murray, Janice, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 41)
  - Ndegwa, J., 1978 (Box-folder 6: 42)
  - Nesvold, Betty A., 1976 (Box-folder 6: 43)
  - Nur, Ismail Musa, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6: 44)
  - Oakley, Robert, 1996 (Box-folder 6: 45)
  - Ojo, Olusola, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 46)
  - Olorunsola, Victor A., 1975, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6: 47)
  - Osman, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 48)
  - Patrick, undated (Box-folder 6: 49)
  - Peterson, Donald, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 50)
  - Pfaller, Alfred, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 51)
  - Press, Robert, 1990-1991, 1996 (Box-folder 6: 52)
  - Price, Melvia, 1978 (Box-folder 6: 53)
  - Prude, Winston B., 1984 (Box-folder 6: 54)
  - Postcards, 1973-1984 (Box-folder 6: 55)
  - Ragsdale, Tod, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 56)
  - Rashid, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 57)
  - Rienner, Lynne, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Roseberg, Carl G., 1976-1977 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Rothchild, Donald, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Roundy, Robert W., 1980 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Saeed, John, 1988 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Samatar, Ahmed I., 1979, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Samatar, Said S., 1980-1989 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Sayid, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Scatton, Carol, undated (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Schneider, Byron, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Schraeder, Peter J., 1989 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Scott, Gerald, 1978 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Seoudy, M. A., 1984, undated (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Serpell, Robert, 1977 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Sheikh-Abdi, Abdi, 1978 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Silinsky, Mark, undated (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Sklar, Richard L., 1983 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Skocpol, Theda, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Slater, Amy, undated (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Smith, Patrick, 1977 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - Stork, Joe and Paul, James, 1977 (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - Suba, M., 1975 (Box-folder 7: 22)
  - Syad, William J. F., undated (Box-folder 7: 23)
  - Tartter, Jean, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 24)
  - Tessler, Mark A., 1984 (Box-folder 7: 25)
  - Thomas, Amy, undated (Box-folder 7: 26)
  - Thomas, Abby, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 7: 27)
  - Thurston, Raymond L., 1978 (Box-folder 7: 28)
  - Tsongas, Paul E., 1983 (Box-folder 7: 29)
  - Turk, Michael, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 30)
  - University of Chicago Press, Politics, Language and Thought: The Somali Experience, publisher correspondence, reviews, promotional materials, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 7: 31)
  - Vickery, Howard, 1978 (Box-folder 7: 32)
  - Victor-Rood, Juliette, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 33)
  - Wais, Ismail, undated (Box-folder 7: 34)
  - Warsama, Abdirahman, H., 1975 (Box-folder 7: 35)
  - Warsama, Ismail Ali, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 36)
  - Waters, Cherri, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 37)
  - Weissman, Steve, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 7: 38)
  - Wiar, Kimberly, 1975 (Box-folder 7: 39)
  - Wolpe, Howard, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 40)
  - Yahya, H. M., 1982 (Box-folder 7: 41)
  - Yallahow, M. A., 1986 (Box-folder 7: 42)
  - Yusuf, Abdinasir S., 1981 (Box-folder 7: 43)
  - Zartman, William I., 1988, 2001 (Box-folder 7: 44)
  - Zerihoun, Taye B., 1976 (Box-folder 7: 45)
  - Zinnes, Dina A., 1982 (Box-folder 7: 46)
  - Zolberg, Aristide R., 1981 (Box-folder 7: 47)
- Subject File, 1966-2006 (Box 7-12)
  - African Language Studies, "The Introduction of a National Orthography for Somali," Andrzejewski, B. W., 1974 (Box-folder 7: 48)
  - Amendment to the Authorization of the Policy Initiatives and Privatization Project (649-0132), 1986 (Box-folder 7: 49)
  - "Arms for the Horn: US Security Policy in Ethiopia and Somalia, 1951-1991," Lefebvre, Jeffrey A. (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "Bargaining Over Objects that Influence Future Bargaining Power," Fearon, James D., 1996 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - "The Bottle and the Bushman," Tagane, Mohamed Said, 1982 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - "African Crisis Areas and United States Foreign Policy," Center for International and Strategic Affairs, UCLA, 1983 March 9-12 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - "New Trends in Somali Poetry," Guled, Abdillahi Deria, Conference of Popular Arts and Media in Africa, 1982 May 17-19 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - "Informal Meeting on Somalia," Conflict Prevention and Peace Forum, 2004 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - "De l'Etat en formation à l'Etat en pointillé: la crise de la regulation politique en Somalie,", undated (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - "Dialectical Differences as an Identity Among Somali Clans," Mohamed, Mukhtar Hassan, 2000 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - "Domestic Anarchy and Civil War," draft, Walter, Barbara F., 1996 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - East Africa, 2005 July (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - "Economic Problems of the Somali Democratic Republic," Gray, Albert L., Jr., 1985 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - "The Emergence and Role of Political Parties in the Inter-River Region of Somalia from 1947 to 1960 (Independence),", undated (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - "The Eritrean Question and Regional Stability in the Horn of Africa," Habteselassie, Bereket, undated (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - "Federal Research Division Research Guide for Country Studies," original and revised, 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - "Trends in the Acquisition and Cataloging of Publications from Somalia," Armstrong, James C., The First International Congress of Somali Studies, 1980 July 6-13 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - First International Congress of Somali Studies, Mogadishu, Somalia, 1980 July 6-13 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - "The French Territory of the Afars and Issas," French government publication, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 8: 17)
  - Friedrich Ebert Stiftung Research Institute conference papers, 1983 (Box-folder 8: 18)
  - "Publications on International Politics and Economics," Friedrich Ebert Stiftung Research Institute, 1983 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - "Symposium: Horn of Africa, from 'Scramble for Africa' to East-West Conflict," Friedrich Ebert Stiftung Research Institute, 1982 June 28-29 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - "High on Marxist Humbug," Togane, Mohamud Siyaad, undated (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - "How to Run an SNM Gauntlet," Samatar, Said S., undated (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - Institute for War and Peace Studies, Columbia University, 1996 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - "International Peacebuilding and the Dynamics of Local and National Reconciliation in Somalia," Menkhaus, Ken, undated (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - "Language, Politics and Thought: The Somali Experience," dissertation, Laitin, David D., undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - "Local Politics and Prospects for Peace Operations,", 1995 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - "Workshop on Intervention in Internal Conflict," National Intelligence Council Project, 2001 July 12 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - "Negotiating Civil Wars: Why Bargains Fail," Walter, Barbara F., undated (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - "Old Sources for New Ideas: The Legacy of Mohammed Abdulle Hassan," Shikh-Abdi, Abdi A., 1991 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - "Case Name: Somalia Ethnic War, 1988-Present," Political Instability Task Force (PITF) Termination Project, 2006 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - "The Political Situation in Somalia and the Prospects for Peace and Stability in the Horn of Africa,", undated (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - "The Politics of Protracted Displacement: A Case Study of the Ogaden Somali Refugees," PhD dissertation, Frederick, Melinda J., 1988 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "Popular Arts and the Media in Africa,", 1982 May 17-19 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - "Power Sharing and International Mediation in Ethnic Conflict," Sisk, Timothy D., 1996 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - "The Problem of Written Somali: A Plan on the Possible Introduction of Written Somali," Galaal, Musa, 1966 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - "Somalia: Black Hawk Down No More," El Koury, Gina, Public International Law and Policy Groups, 2002 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - "The Qat Eaters," Hussein, Abdi, 1982 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - "Rebuttal of Professor David Laitin's Paper on Somalia,", 1984 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - "Recommended Relief Strategy for Kenya," Cuny, Frederick C., undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - "Recommended Strategy for the Somali Emergency," Cuny, Frederick C., undated (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - "The Recurring Debate over Female Circumcision," draft, Geshekter, Charles, 1986 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Remarks before the House Subcommittee on Africa, Walker, Lannon, 1981 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - "Report on an Emergency Needs Assessment of the Lower Jubba Region (Kismaayo, Jamaame, and Jilib Districts), Somalia," Menkhaus, Kenneth, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - Second International Congress of Somali Studies, Hamburg, Germany, 1983 August 1-6 (Box-folder 10: 13)
  - "Informal Meeting on Somalia," Social Science Research Council (SSRC) Conflict Prevention and Peace Forum, 2004 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - "Socialist Politics in Revolutionary Ethiopia," Harberson, John W., 1976 (Box-folder 10: 15)
  - Somali Future (Aayaha Soomaliya), Newsletter of the Somali Studies Association of North America, 1992 (Box-folder 10: 16)